# Upendra Dilip Shukla

### **SUMMARY**

Productivity-driven Business Analyst and Management Professional with experience in designing, development and execution of Business Projects and Processes. Total 15 years of experience in Banking (HSBC and Standard Chartered Bank), Insurance (Religare and ICICI Prudential), Finance and Real Estate.

#### **SKILLS POSSESSED**

#### Business Analysis:

Business and Functional Requirement gathering and analysis

Effective coordination with stakeholders to develop and implement solution based tasks.

Process Modelling and collaborating with Functional Managers

Precise Documentation and Prompt Reporting

#### Project Management:

Project Designing and Resource Planning

Coordination with Functional Departments and Vendors for functional implementation

Tracking Work-in-progress through necessary documentation and periodic meetings

Performance Analysis and Reporting on ERP Tool

#### > Domain Knowledge:

**Banking** – Retail Banking (Assets and Liabilities), Corporate Banking, Wealth Products,

Operations and Compliance, Banking Standards, etc.

**Insurance** – Core Concepts, Products, Underwriting, Operations, Claim Settlement,

Distribution, Regulations and Compliance

Real Estate – Project Management of Residential and Commercial Property, Project Finance.

## > Technical Skills:

Proficient in MS Office and SQL

Knowledge of Analytical and Visualization Tools - SAS, R, Python, MS Visio, Tableau, PowerBI.

#### > Interpersonal Skills:

Impactful Verbal and Written Communication Skills

Leadership in fulfilling commitments collectively

Collaborative Attitude within Team

Attention to details and Analytical Thinking

Quick Learner and acumen to upskill constantly

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

#### 1. Business Analyst (Freelance) at VDS MANAGEMENT CONSULTANTS, PUNE

Duration - 1st July, 2016 till date

- Developed Customer Relationship Management (CRM) Software for Real Estate Firms in Pune to ensure efficient management of customer enquiries, marketing communication and Consumer Lifecycle Management.
- Integration of Digital Marketing Strategies in CRM Software.
- Consulted Firms in Real Estate Project Planning, Business Process Modelling, Functional Segregation, Business Documentation, Business Strategy implementation and monitoring, etc.
- Engage Clients to gather Business and Functional Requirements through Document Analysis, Interviews and Workflow Analysis.
- Develop Business Architecture using Scope, Activity Diagrams, Alternatives and Risk Analysis.
- Disseminate Business requirements to various Functional/Resourcing Teams by constructing simplified Process Models using UML tools like MS Visio, MS PowerPoint, etc.
- Integration of new Technological initiatives and Strategies in Project Marketing to ensure economic optimization.

#### 2. Head Consultant (Freelance) at VDS PROPERY CONSULTANTS, PUNE

Duration – 1st June, 2013 to 30th June, 2016

- Gathering Functional and Product Requirements from Clients and Collaborate with various Business Agencies to fulfil these requirements.
- Financial Consultation for Project Funding and Home Finance to end users.
- Integration of new Technological initiatives and Strategies in Project Marketing to ensure economic optimization of plans.
- Performance Analysis, Training and Development of Team Members.
- Achieved 400% growth from 2013 to 2016 by acquiring Real Estate Projects as Sole Consultant

# **3.** Preferred Banking Relationship Manager at STANDARD CHARTERED BANK, Kalyani Nagar, Pune Duration – 20<sup>th</sup> November, 2009 to 27<sup>th</sup> May, 2013

- Understanding Financial Requirements of High Net-Worth Individual (HNI) and collaborating with different Banking Departments to deliver Financial Solutions.
- Products sourced Retail Banking Products, Wholesale Banking Products, Investment Securities, Insurance, Private Equities, Secured and Unsecured Loans (Retail), Foreign Exchange, etc.
- Assisting Product Development Teams in developing CRM tools for Sales Performance Analysis.
- · Business Compliance and Regulatory Reporting.
- Have achieved the BEST PFM award for Investment Sales in June, 2011 across India.

# 4. Business Development Manager at AEGON Religare life Insurance, Pune.

Duration – 1st October, 2008 – 20th September, 2009

- Recruiting a team of 8 Relationship Manager (RM) who would understand client requirements and offer Insurance solutions.
- Training the RMs on Communication Techniques and Product Recommendation.
- Conducting Promotional Activities and Events to attract Sales Enquiries.

- Continual Performance Analysis of all Team Members to ensure their Growth.
- Ranked No1 BDM across India in sourcing riders with percentage achievement more than 100% in AEGON Religare.

#### 5. Financial Planning Manager at HSBC Bank Ltd, Law College Road, Pune.

Duration - March, 2007 to October, 2008

- Financial Planning of clients and Coordination between different Banking Departments to deliver investment solutions pertaining to Insurance, Mutual Funds and banking products.
- Assist CRM Officer to improvise and develop Customer Relationship Management System (CRMS)
- Internal Functions in the branch such as Internal Audit, Periodic Checks on Procedure Adherence and Reporting to Branch Head on all these Reports.
- Received a certificate and award for delivering excellent customer service from the company and the customer both in December 2007 in HSBC.

#### 6. Life Insurance Advisor at ICICI Prudential Life Insurance Co. Ltd, Pune.

Duration -November, 2002 - September, 2006

• Identifying prospects for insurance products and offering suitable insurance products.

#### **ACADEMIC QUALIFICATIONS**

ACADEMIC QUALIFICATIONS	MONTH & YEAR OF PASSING	UNIVERSITY / BOARD	NAME OF THE INSTITUTION	PASSING CLASS
M.M.M. (Master in Marketing Management)	May 2007	Savitribai Phule Pune University	Indsearch, Pune	FIRST CLASS
B.Com	May 2005	Savitribai Phule Pune University	I.M.V. College, Talegaon, Pune	FIRST CLASS
H.S.C. (Commerce)	March, 2002	Maharashtra Board	I.M.V. College, Talegaon, Pune	FIRST CLASS
S.S.C.	March, 2000	Maharashtra Board	Mt. St. Anne Convent School, Talegaon, Pune	FIRST CLASS

#### TRAININGS AND CERTIFICATIONS

- Certifications from Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority (IRDA) and Association of Mutual Funds in India (AMFI)
- Successfully undergone respective trainings from HSBC Bank and Standard Chartered Bank on Banking Regulations, Operations and Risk Management.
- Qualified in National Eligibility Test (NET), a doctoral level Test based on Logical reasoning, analytical thinking and Functional Knowledge of Management.

#### PERSONAL DETAILS

- Date of Birth: 20<sup>TH</sup> AUGUST, 1984
- Marital Status: Married
- Residential Address: 'Guruprasad', Plot No. 43, Harneshwar Society, Talegaon Dabhade, Pune 410507
- Languages Known English, Hindi, Marathi
- Active participation and winner in many local and cultural activities since school days.